<title>De Cive</title>
by <author>Thomas Hobbes</author>
<subheading>Philosophicall Elements of a true Citizen.
Liberty</subheading>

<excerpt>
    <chapter>Chapter I. Of the state of men without Civill Society</chapter>
    
<section>I.</section> 
    The faculties of Humane nature may be reduc'd unto four kinds; Bodily strength, Experience, Reason, Passion.
Taking the beginning of this following Doctrine from these, we will declare in the first place what manner of
inclinations men who are endued with these faculties bare towards each other, and whether, and by what faculty,
they are born apt for Society, and so preserve themselves against mutuall violence; then proceeding, we will shew
what advice was necessary to be taken for this businesse, and what are the conditions of Society, or of Humane
Peace; that is to say, (changing the words onely) what are the fundamentall Lawes of Nature.

<section>II.</section> 
    The greatest part of those men who have written ought concerning Commonwealths, either suppose, or require
us, or beg of us to believe, That Man is a Creature born fit [1] for Society: The Greeks call him Zoon politikon,
and on this foundation they so build up the Doctrine of Civill Society, as if for the preservation of Peace, and the
Government of Man−kind there were nothing else necessary, than that Men should agree to make certaine
Covenants and Conditions together, which themselves should then call Lawes. Which Axiom, though received by
most, is yet certainly False, and an Errour proceeding from our too slight contemplation of Humane Nature; for
they who shall more narrowly look into the Causes for which Men come together, and delight in each others
company, shall easily find that this happens not because naturally it could happen no otherwise, but by Accident:
For if by nature one Man should Love another (that is) as Man, there could no reason be return'd why every Man
should not equally Love every Man, as being equally Man, or why he should rather frequent those whose Society
affords him Honour or Profit. We doe not therefore by nature seek Society for its own sake, but that we may
receive some Honour or Profit from it; these we desire Primarily, that Secondarily: How by what advice Men doe
meet, will be best known by observing those things which they doe when they are met: For if they meet for
Traffique, it's plaine every man regards not his Fellow, but his Businesse; if to discharge some Office, a certain
Market−friendship is begotten, which hath more of Jealousie in it than True love, and whence Factions sometimes
may arise, but Good will never; if for Pleasure, and Recreation of mind, every man is wont to please himself most
with those things which stirre up laughter, whence he may (according to the nature of that which is Ridiculous) by
comparison of another mans Defects and Infirmities, passe the more currant in his owne opinion; and although
this be sometimes innocent, and without offence; yet it is manifest they are not so much delighted with the
Society, as their own Vain glory. But for the most part, in these kind of meetings, we wound the absent; their
whole life, sayings, actions are examin'd, judg'd, condemn'd; nay, it is very rare, but some present receive a fling
before they part, so as his reason was not ill, who was wont alwayes at parting to goe out last. And these are
indeed the true delights of Society, unto which we are carryed by nature, (i.e.) by those passions which are
incident to all Creatures, untill either by sad experience, or good precepts, it so fall out (which in many never
happens) that the Appetite, of present matters, be dul'd with the memory of things past, without which, the
discourse of most quick and nimble men, on this subject, is but cold and hungry.
But if it so happen, that being met, they passe their time in relating some Stories, and one of them begins to tell
one which concernes himselfe; instantly every one of the rest most greedily desires to speak of himself too; if one
relate some wonder, the rest will tell you miracles, if they have them, if not, they'l fein them: Lastly, that I may
say somewhat of them who pretend to be wiser than others; if they meet to talk of Philosophy, look how many
men, so many would be esteem'd Masters, or else they not only love not their fellowes, but even persecute them
with hatred: So clear is it by experience to all men who a little more narrowly consider Humane affaires, that all
free congress ariseth either from mutual poverty, or from vain glory, whence the parties met, endeavour to carry
with them either some benefit, or to leave behind them that same eudokimein, some esteem and honour with
those, with whom they have been conversant: The same is also collected by reason out of the definitions
themselves, of Will, Good, Honour, Profitable. For when we voluntarily contract Society, in all manner of Society
we look after the object of the Will, i.e. that, which every one of those, who gather together, propounds to
himselfe for good; now whatsoever seemes good, is pleasant, and relates either to the senses, or the mind, but all
the mindes pleasure is either Glory, (or to have a good opinion of ones selfe) or referres to Glory in the end; the
rest are Sensuall, or conducing to sensuality, which may be all comprehended under the word Conveniencies. All
Society therefore is either for Gain, or for Glory; (i.e.) not so much for love of our Fellowes, as for love of our
Selves: but no society can be great, or lasting, which begins from Vain Glory; because that Glory is like Honour,
if all men have it, no man hath it, for they consist in comparison and precellence; neither doth the society of others
advance any whit the cause of my glorying in my selfe; for every man must account himself, such as he can make
himselfe, without the help of others. But though the benefits of this life may be much farthered by mutuall help,
since yet those may be better attain'd to by Dominion, than by the society of others: I hope no body will doubt but
that men would much more greedily be carryed by Nature, if all fear were removed, to obtain Dominion, than to
gaine Society. We must therefore resolve, that the Originall of all great, and lasting Societies, consisted not in the
mutuall good will men had towards each other, but in the mutuall fear [2] they had of each other.

<section>III.</section> 
    The cause of mutuall fear consists partly in the naturall equality of men, partly in their mutuall will of hurting:
whence it comes to passe that we can neither expect from others, nor promise to our selves the least security: For
if we look on men fullgrown, and consider how brittle the frame of our humane body is, (which perishing, all its
strength, vigour, and wisdome it selfe perisheth with it) and how easie a matter it is, even for the weakest man to
kill the strongest, there is no reason why any man trusting to his own strength should conceive himself made by
nature above others: they are equalls who can doe equall things one against the other; but they who can do the
greatest things, (namely kill) can doe equall things. All men therefore among themselves are by nature equall; the
inequality we now discern, hath its spring from the Civill Law.

<section>IV.</section>
    All men in the State of nature have a desire, and will to hurt, but not proceeding from the same cause, neither
equally to be condemn'd; for one man according to that naturall equality which is among us, permits as much to
others, as he assumes to himself (which is an argument of a temperate man, and one that rightly values his
power); another, supposing himselfe above others, will have a License to doe what he lists, and challenges
Respect, and Honour, as due to him before others, (which is an Argument of a fiery spirit:) This mans will to hurt
ariseth from Vain glory, and the false esteeme he hath of his owne strength; the other's, from the necessity of
defending himselfe, his liberty, and his goods against this mans violence.

<section>V.</section> 
    Furthermore, since the combate of Wits is the fiercest, the greatest discords which are, must necessarily arise
from this Contention; for in this case it is not only odious to contend against, but also not to consent; for not to
approve of what a man saith is no lesse than tacitely to accuse him of an Errour in that thing which he speaketh; as
in very many things to dissent, is as much as if you accounted him a fool whom you dissent from; which may
appear hence, that there are no Warres so sharply wag'd as between Sects of the same Religion, and Factions of
the same Commonweale, where the Contestation is Either concerning Doctrines, or Politique Prudence. And since
all the pleasure, and jollity of the mind consists in this; even to get some, with whom comparing, it may find
somewhat wherein to Tryumph, and Vaunt it self; its impossible but men must declare sometimes some mutuall
scorn and contempt either by Laughter, or by Words, or by Gesture, or some signe or other; than which there is no
greater vexation of mind; and than from which there cannot possibly arise a greater desire to doe hurt.

<section>VI.</section> 
    But the most frequent reason why men desire to hurt each other, ariseth hence, that many men at the same
time have an Appetite to the same thing; which yet very often they can neither enjoy in common, nor yet divide it;
whence it followes that the strongest must have it, and who is strongest must be decided by the Sword.

<section>VII.</section> 
    Among so many dangers therefore, as the naturall lusts of men do daily threaten each other withall, to have a
care of ones selfe is not a matter so scornfully to be lookt upon, as if so be there had not been a power and will left
in one to have done otherwise; for every man is desirous of what is good for him, and shuns what is evill, but
chiefly the chiefest of naturall evills, which is Death; and this he doth, by a certain impulsion of nature, no lesse
than that whereby a Stone moves downward: It is therefore neither absurd, nor reprehensible; neither against the
dictates of true reason for a man to use all his endeavours to preserve and defend his Body, and the Members
thereof from death and sorrowes; but that which is not contrary to right reason, that all men account to be done
justly, and with right; Neither by the word Right is any thing else signified, than that liberty which every man hath
to make use of his naturall faculties according to right reason: Therefore the first foundation of naturall Right is
this, That every man as much as in him lies endeavour to protect his life and members.

<section>VIII.</section> 
    But because it is in vaine for a man to have a Right to the end, if the Right to the necessary meanes be
deny'd him; it followes, that since every man hath a Right to preserve himself, he must also be allowed a Right to
use all the means, and do all the actions, without which He cannot Preserve himself.

<section>IX.</section> 
    Now whether the means which he is about to use, and the action he is performing, be necessary to the
preservation of his Life, and Members, or not, he Himself, by the right of nature, must be judg; for say another
man, judg that it is contrary to right reason that I should judg of mine own perill: why now, because he judgeth of
what concerns me, by the same reason, because we are equall by nature, will I judge also of things which doe
belong to him; therefore it agrees with right reason (that is) it is the right of nature that I judge of his opinion,
(i.e.) whether it conduce to my preservation, or not.

<section>X.</section> 
    Nature hath given to every one a right to all. That is it was lawfull for every man in the bare state of nature, [3]
or before such time as men had engag'd themselves by any Covenants, or Bonds, to doe what hee would, and
against whom he thought fit, and to possesse, use, and enjoy all what he would, or could get. Now because
whatsoever a man would, it therefore seems good to him because he wills it, and either it really doth, or at least
seems to him to contribute toward his preservation, (but we have already allowed him to be judge in the foregoing
Article whether it doth or not, in so much as we are to hold all for necessary whatsoever he shall esteeme so) and
by the 7. Article it appeares that by the right of Nature those things may be done, and must be had, which
necessarily conduce to the protection of life, and members, it followes, that in the state of nature, To have all, and
do all is lawfull for all. And this is that which is meant by that common saying, Nature hath given all to all, from
whence we understand likewise, that in the state of nature, Profit is the measure of Right.

<section>XI.</section> 
    But it was the least benefit for men thus to have a common Right to all things; for the effects of this Right are
the same, almost, as if there had been no Right at all; for although any man might say of every thing, This is mine,
yet could he not enjoy it, by reason of his Neighbour, who having equall Right, and equall power, would pretend
the same thing to be his.

<section>XII.</section> 
    If now to this naturall proclivity of men, to hurt each other, which they derive from their Passions, but chiefly
from a vain esteeme of themselves: You adde, the right of all to all, wherewith one by right invades, the other by
right resists, and whence arise perpetuall jealousies and suspicions on all hands, and how hard a thing it is to
provide against an enemy invading us, with an intention to oppresse, and ruine, though he come with a small
Number, and no great Provision; it cannot be deny'd but that the naturall state of men, before they entr'd into
Society, was a meer War, and that not simply, but a War of all men, against all men; for what is WAR, but that
same time in which the will of contesting by force, is fully declar'd either by Words, or Deeds? The time
remaining, is termed PEACE.

<section>XIII.</section> 
    But it is easily judg'd how disagreeable a thing to the preservation either of Man−kind, or of each single
Man, a perpetuall War is: But it is perpetuall in its own nature, because in regard of the equality of those that
strive, it cannot be ended by Victory; for in this state the Conquerour is subject to so much danger, as it were to be
accounted a Miracle, if any, even the most strong should close up his life with many years, and old age. They of
America are Examples hereof, even in this present Age: Other Nations have been in former Ages, which now
indeed are become Civill, and Flourishing, but were then few, fierce, short−lived, poor, nasty, and destroy'd of all
that Pleasure, and Beauty of life, which Peace and Society are wont to bring with them. Whosoever therefore
holds, that it had been best to have continued in that state in which all things were lawfull for all men, he
contradicts himself; for every man, by naturall necessity desires that which is good for him: nor is there any that
esteemes a war of all against all, which necessarily adheres to such a State, to be good for him. And so it happens
that through feare of each other we think it fit to rid our selves of this condition, and to get some fellowes; that if
there needs must be war, it may not yet be against all men, nor without some helps.

<section>XIV.</section> 
    Fellowes are gotten either by constraint, or by consent; By Constraint, when after fight the Conqueror makes
the conquered serve him either through feare of death, or by laying fetters on him: By consent, when men enter
into society to helpe each other, both parties consenting without any constraint. But the Conqueror may by right
compell the Conquered, or the strongest the weaker, (as a man in health may one that is sick, or he that is of riper
yeares a childe) unlesse he will choose to die, to give caution of his future obedience. For since the right of
protecting our selves according to our owne wills proceeded from our danger, and our danger from our equality,
its more consonant to reason, and more certaine for our conservation, using the present advantage to secure our
selves by taking caution; then, when they shall be full growne and strong, and got out of our power, to endeavour
to recover that power againe by doubtfull fight. And on the other side, nothing can be thought more absurd, than
by discharging whom you already have weak in your power, to make him at once both an enemy, and a strong
one. From whence we may understand likewise as a Corollarie in the naturall state of men, That a sure and
irresistible Power confers the right of Dominion, and ruling over those who cannot resist; insomuch, as the right
of all things, that can be done, adheres essentially, and immediately unto this omnipotence hence arising.

<section>XV.</section> 
    Yet cannot men expect any lasting preservation continuing thus in the state of nature (i.e.) of War, by reason
of that equality of power, and other humane faculties they are endued withall. Wherefore to seek Peace, where
there is any hopes of obtaining it, and where there is none, to enquire out for Auxiliaries of War, is the dictate of
right Reason; that is, the Law of Nature, as shall be shewed in the next Chapter.

<divider>____________</divider>
<footer>1. Born fit.</footer> 
    Since we now see actually a constituted Society among men, and none living out of it, since we discern all desirous 
    of congresse, and mutuall correspondence, it may seeme a wonderfull kind of stupidity, to lay in the very threshold 
    of this Doctrine, such a stumbling block before the Readers, as to deny Man to be born fit for Society: Therefore I 
    must more plainly say, That it is true indeed, that to Man, by nature, or as Man, that is, as soone as he is born, 
    Solitude is an enemy; for Infants have need of others to help them to live, and those of riper years to help them to 
    live well, wherefore I deny not that men (even nature compelling) desire to come together. But civill Societies are 
    not meer Meetings, but Bonds, to the making whereof, Faith and Compacts are necessary: The Vertue whereof to Children, 
    and Fooles, and the profit whereof to those who have not yet tasted the miseries which accompany its defects, is 
    altogether unknown; whence it happens, that those, because they know not what Society is, cannot enter into it; these, 
    because ignorant of the benefit it brings, care not for it. Manifest therefore it is, that all men, because they are 
    born in Infancy, are born unapt for Society. Many also (perhaps most men) either through defect of minde, or want of 
    education remain unfit during the whole course of their lives; yet have Infants, as well as those of riper years, an 
    humane nature; wherefore Man is made fit for Society not by Nature, but by Education: furthermore, although Man were 
    born in such a condition as to desire it, it followes not, that he therefore were Born fit to enter into it; for it is 
    one thing to desire, another to be in capacity fit for what we desire; for even they, who through their pride, will not 
    stoop to equall conditions, without which there can be no Society, do yet desire it.

<footer>2. The mutuall fear.</footer> 
    It is objected: It is so improbable that men should grow into civill Societies out of fear, that if they had been 
    afraid, they would not have endur'd each others looks: They Presume, I believe, that to fear is nothing else than 
    to be affrighted: I comprehend in this word Fear, a certain foresight of future evill; neither doe I conceive flight 
    the sole property of fear, but to distrust, suspect, take heed, provide so that they may not fear, is also incident 
    to the fearfull. They who go to Sleep, shut their Dores; they who Travell carry their Swords with them, because they 
    fear Theives. Kingdomes guard their Coasts and Frontiers with Forts, and Castles; Cities are compact with Walls, and 
    all for fear of neighbouring Kingdomes and Townes; even the strongest Armies, and most accomplisht for Fight, yet 
    sometimes Parly for Peace, as fearing each others Power, and lest they might be overcome. It is through fear that men 
    secure themselves, by flight indeed, and in corners, if they think they cannot escape otherwise, but for the most part 
    by Armes, and Defensive Weapons; whence it happens, that daring to come forth, they know each others Spirits; but then, 
    if they fight, Civill Society ariseth from the Victory, if they agree, from their Agreement.

<footer>3. In the bare state of Nature.</footer> 
    This is thus to be understood: What any man does in the bare state of Nature is injurious to no man; not that 
    in such a State he cannot offend God, or break the Lawes of Nature; for Injustice against men presupposeth 
    Humane Lawes, such, as in the State of Nature there are none: Now the truth of this proposition thus conceived 
    is sufficiently demonstrated to the mindfull Reader in the Articles immediately foregoing; but because in 
    certaine cases the difficulty of the conclusion makes us forget the premises, I will contract this Argument, 
    and make it most evident to a single view; every man hath right to protect himself, as appears by the seventh 
    Article. The same man therefore hath a right to use all the means which necessarily conduce to this end by the 
    eight Article: But those are the necessary means which he shall judge to be such by the ninth Article. He therefore 
    hath a right to make use, of and to doe all whatsoever he shall judge requisite for his preservation: wherefore by 
    the judgement of him that doth it, the thing done is either right, or wrong; and therefore right. True it is 
    therefore in the bare State of Nature, But if any man pretend somewhat to tend necessarily to his preservation, 
    which yet he himself doth not confidently believe so, he may offend against the Lawes of Nature, as in the third 
    Chapter of this Book is more at large declar'd. It hath been objected by some: If a Sonne kill his Father, doth he 
    him no injury? I have answered, That a Sonne cannot be understood to be at any time in the State of Nature, as being 
    under the Power and command of them to whom he ownes his protection as soon as ever he is born, namely either his 
    Fathers, or his Mothers, or his that nourisht him, as is demonstrated in the ninth Chapter.

<chapter>Chapter II. Of the Law of Nature concerning Contracts</chapter>
    
<section>I.</section> 
    All Authors agree not concerning the definition of the Naturall Law, who notwithstanding doe very often make
use of this terme in their Writings. The Method therefore, wherein we begin from definitions, and exclusion of all
equivocation, is only proper to them who leave no place for contrary Disputes; for the rest, if any man say, that
somwhat is done against the Law of Nature, one proves it hence, because it was done against the generall
Agreement of all the most wise, and learned Nations: But this declares not who shall be the judg of the wisdome
and learning of all Nations: Another hence, That it was done against the Generall consent of all Man−kind; which
definition is by no means to be admitted; for then it were impossible for any but Children, and Fools, to offend
against such a Law; for sure, under the notion of Man−kind, they comprehend all men actually endued with
Reason. These therefore either doe Naught against it, or if they doe Ought, it is without their joint accord, and
therefore ought to be excus'd; but to receive the Lawes of Nature from the Consents of them, who oftner Break,
than Observe them, is in truth unreasonable: besides, Men condemne the same things in others, which they
approve in themselves; on the other side, they publickly commend what they privately condemne; and they
deliver their Opinions more by Hear−say, than any Speculation of their own; and they accord more through hatred
of some object, through fear, hope, love, or some other perturbation of mind, than true Reason. And therefore it
comes to passe, that whole Bodyes of people often doe those things by Generall accord, or Contention, which
those Writers most willingly acknowledge to be against the Law of Nature. But since all doe grant that is done by
RIGHT, which is not done against Reason, we ought to judg those Actions onely wrong, which are repugnant to
right Reason, (i.e.) which contradict some certaine Truth collected by right reasoning from true Principles; but
that Wrong which is done, we say it is done against some Law: therefore True Reason is a certaine Law, which
(since it is no lesse a part of Humane nature, than any other faculty, or affection of the mind) is also termed
naturall. Therefore the Law of Nature, that I may define it, is the Dictate of right Reason, [1] conversant about
those things which are either to be done, or omitted for the constant preservation of Life, and Members, as much
as in us lyes.

<section>II.</section> 
    But the first and fundamentall Law of Nature is, That Peace is to be sought after where it may be found; and
where not, there to provide our selves for helps of War: For we shewed in the last Article of the foregoing
Chapter, that this precept is the dictate of right reason; but that the Dictates of right reason are naturall Lawes, that
hath been newly prov'd above; But this is the first, because the rest are deriv'd from this, and they direct the wayes
either to Peace, or self−defence.

<section>III. </section>
    But one of the Naturall Lawes deriv'd from this fundamentall one is this, That the right of all men, to all
things, ought not to be retain'd, but that some certain rights ought to be transferr'd, or relinquisht: for if every one
should retain his right to all things, it must necessarily follow, that some by right might invade; and others, by the
same right, might defend themselves against them, (for every man, by naturall necessity, endeavours to defend his
Body, and the things which he judgeth necessary towards the protection of his Body) therefore War would follow.
He therefore acts against the reason of Peace, (i.e.) against the Law of Nature, whosoever he be, that doth not part
with his Right to all things.

<section>IV.</section> 
    But he is said to part with his right, who either absolutely renounceth it, or conveys it to another. He
absolutely renounceth it, who by some sufficient Signe, or meet Tokens, declares that he is willing that it shall
never be lawfull for him to doe that again, which before, by Right, he might have done; but he conveys it to
another, who by some sufficient Signe, or meet Tokens, declares to that other, that he is willing it should be
unlawfull for him to resist him, in going about to do somewhat in the performance where he might before, with
Right, have resisted him; but that the conveyance of Right consists meerly in not resisting, is understood by this,
that before it was convey'd, he, to whom he convey'd it, had even then also a right to all, whence he could not give
any new Right: But the resisting Right he had, before he gave it, by reason whereof the other could not freely
enjoy his Rights, is utterly abolisht: Whosoever therefore acquires some Right in the naturall state of men, he
onely procures himself security, and freedome from just molestation in the enjoyment of his Primitive Right: As
for example, if any man shall sell, or give away a Farme, he utterly deprives himself only from all Right to this
Farme, but he does not so from others also.

<section>V.</section>
    But in the conveyance of Right the will is requisite not onely of him that conveys, but of him also that accepts
it. If either be wanting, the Right remaines: for if I would have given what was mine, to one who refus'd to accept
of it, I have not therefore either simply renounc'd my Right, or convey'd it to any man; for the cause which mov'd
me to part with it to this Man was in him onely, not in others too.

<section>VI.</section> 
    But if there be no other Token extant of our will either to quit, or convey our Right, but onely Words; those
words must either relate to the present, or time past; for if they be of the future onely, they convey nothing: for
example, he that speaks thus of the time to come, I will give to morrow, declares openly that yet he hath not given
it; so that all this day his right remains, and abides to morrow too, unlesse in the interim he actually bestowes it:
for what is mine, remains mine till I have parted with it. But if I shall speak of the time present, suppose thus; I
doe give, or have given you this to be received to morrow, by these words is signified that I have already given it,
and that his Right to receive it to morrow, is conveyed to him by me to day.

<section>VII.</section> 
    Neverthelesse, although words alone are not sufficient tokens to declare the Will; if yet to words relating to
the future, there shall some other signes be added, they may become as valid, as if they had been spoken of the
present: If therefore, as by reason of those other signes, it appear, that he that speaks of the future, intends those
words should be effectuall toward the perfect transferring of his Right, they ought to be valid; for the conveyance
of right depends not on words, but (as hath been instanc'd in the 4. Article) on the declaration of the Will.

<section>VIII.</section> 
    If any man conveigh some part of his right to another, and doth not this for some certain benefit received, or
for some compact, a conveighance in this kind is called a Gift, or free Donation. But in free donation those words
onely oblige us which signifie the present, or the time past; for if they respect the future, they oblige not as words,
for the reason given in the foregoing Article: It must needs therefore be, that the Obligation arise from some other
tokens of the Will: But, because whatsoever is voluntarily done, is done for some good to him that wils it; there
can no other token be assigned of the Will to give it, except some benefit either already receiv'd, or to be acquir'd;
but is suppos'd, that no such benefit is acquired, nor any compact in being; for if so, it would cease to be a free
gift: It remains therefore, that a mutuall good turne without agreement be expected; but no signe can be given, that
he, who us'd future words toward him who was in no sort engag'd to return a benefit, should desire to have his
words so understood, as to oblige himselfe thereby. Nor is it suitable to Reason, that those who are easily enclined
to doe well to others, should be oblig'd by every promise, testifying their present good affection: And for this
cause, a promiser in this kind, must be understood to have time to deliberate, and power to change that affection
as well as he to whom he made that promise, may alter his desert. But he that deliberates, is so farre forth free, nor
can be said to have already given: But if he promise often, and yet give seldome, he ought to be condemn'd of
levity, and be called not a Donour, but Doson.

<section>IX.</section> 
    But the act of two, or more, mutually conveighing their Rights, is call'd a Contract. But in every Contract,
either both parties instantly performe what they contract for, insomuch as there is no trust had from either to
other; or the one performes, the other is trusted, or neither performe. Where both parties performe presently, there
the Contract is ended, as soon as 'tis performed; but where there is credit given either to one, or both, there the
party trusted promiseth after−performance; and this kind of promise is called a COVENANT.

<section>X.</section> 
    But the Covenant made by the party trusted with him, who hath already performed, although the promise be
made by words pointing at the future, doth no lesse transfer the right of future time, than if it had been made by
words signifying the present, or time past: for the others performance is a most manifest signe that he so
understood the speech of him whom he trusted, as that he would certainly make performance also at the appointed
time; and by this signe the party trusted knew himselfe to be thus understood, which, because he hindred not,
'twas an evident token of his Will to performe. The promises therefore which are made for some benefit received
(which are also Covenants) are Tokens of the Will; that is, (as in the foregoing Section hath been declared) of the
last act of deliberating, whereby the liberty of non−performance is abolisht, and by consequence are obligatory;
for where Liberty ceaseth, there beginneth Obligation.

<section>XI.</section> 
    But the Covenants, which are made in contract of mutuall trust, neither party performing out of hand, if there
arise [2] a just suspicion in either of them, are in the state of nature invalid: for he that first performes by reason of
the wicked disposition of the greatest part of men studying their owne advantage, either by right, or wrong,
exposeth himself to the perverse will of him with whom he hath Contracted; for it suites not with reason, that any
man should performe first, if it be not likely that the other will make good his promise after; which, whether it be
probable, or not, he that doubts it, must be judge of, as hath been shewed in the foregoing Chapter in the 9.
Article. Thus, I say, things stand in the state of nature, but in a Civill State, when there is a power which can
compell both parties, he that hath contracted to perform first, must first performe; because, that since the other
may be compell'd, the cause which made him fear the others non−performance, ceaseth.

<section>XII.</section> 
    But from this reason, that in all Free−gifts, and Compacts, there is an acceptance of the conveighance of
Right required: it followes, that no man can Compact with him who doth not declare his acceptance; and therefore
we cannot compact with Beasts, neither can we give, or take from them any manner of Right, by reason of their
want of speech, and understanding, Neither can any man Covenant with God, or be oblig'd to him by Vow, except
so far forth as it appeares to him by Holy Scriptures, that he hath substituted certaine men who have authority to
accept of such like Vowes and Covenants, as being in Gods stead.

<section>XIII.</section> 
    Those therefore doe vow in vain, who are in the state of nature, where they are not tyed by any Civill Law,
(except by most certain Revelation the Will of God to accept their Vow, or Pact, be made known to them) for if
what they Vow, be contrary to the Law of Nature, they are not tyed by their Vow, for no man is tyed to perform
an unlawfull act; but if what is vowed, be commanded by some Law of nature, it is not their Vow, but the Law it
self which ties them; but if he were free before his vow, either to doe it, or not doe it, his liberty remaines, because
that the openly declar'd Will of the obliger is requisite to make an obligation by Vow, which in the case
propounded is suppos'd not to be: Now I call him the Obliger to whom any one is tyed, and the Obliged him who
is tyed.

<section>XIV.</section> 
    Covenants are made of such things onely as fall under our deliberation, for it can be no Covenant without
the Will of the Contractor, but the Will is the last act of him who deliberates; therefore they onely concerne things
possible, and to come; no man therefore, by his Compact, obligeth himself to an impossibility. But yet, though we
often Covenant to doe such things as then seem' d possible when we promis'd them, which yet afterward appear to
be impossible, are we therefore freed from all obligation? The reason whereof is, that he who promiseth a future
incertainty receives a present benefit; on condition, that he return another for it: for his Will, who performes the
present benefit hath simply before it, for its object, a certain good [equally] valuable with the thing promised; but
the thing it selfe not simply, but with condition if it could be done; but if it should so happen, that even this should
prove impossible, why then he must perform as much as he can. Covenants therefore oblige us not to perform just
the thing it selfe covenanted for, but our utmost endeavour; for this onely is, the things themselves are not in our
power.

<section>XV.</section> 
    We are freed from Covenants two wayes, either by performing, or by being forgiven: By performing, for
beyond that we oblig'd not our selves. By being forgiven, because he whom we oblig'd our selves to by forgiving,
is conceiv'd to return us that Right which we past over to him; for, forgiving, implies giving: that is, by the fourth
Article of this Chapter, a conveyance of Right to him to whom the gift is made.

<section>XVI.</section> 
    Its an usuall question, Whether Compacts extorted from us, through fear, do oblige, or not: For example, If
to redeeme my life, from the power of a Robber, I promise to pay him 100 l. next day; and that I will doe no act
whereby to apprehend, and bring him to Justice, whether I am tyed to keep promise, or not? But though such a
Promise must sometimes be judged to be of no effect, yet it is not to be accounted so, because it proceeded from
fear, for then it would follow that those promises which reduc'd men to a civill life, and by which Lawes were
made, might likewise be of none effect, (for it proceeds from fear of mutuall slaughter, that one man submits
himselfe to the Dominion of another:) And he should play the fool finely, who should trust his captive
covenanting with the price of his redemption. It holds universally true, that promises doe oblige when there is
some benefit received; and that to promisee and the thing promised, be lawfull: But it is lawfull, for the
redemption of my life, both to promise, and to give what I will of mine owne to any man, even to a Thief. We are
oblig'd therefore, by promises proceeding from fear, except the Civill Law forbid them, by vertue whereof, that
which is promised becomes unlawfull.

<section>XVII.</section> 
    Whosoever shall contract with one to doe, or omit somewhat, and shall after Covenant the contrary with
another; he maketh not the former, but the latter Contract unlawfull: for, he hath no longer Right to doe, or to omit
ought, who by former Contracts hath conveyed it to another; wherefore he can conveigh no Right by latter
Contracts, and what is promised, is promis'd without Right: He is therefore tyed onely to his first Contract; to
break which is unlawfull.

<section>XVIII.</section> 
    No man is oblig'd by any Contracts whatsoever not to resist him who shall offer to kill, wound, or any
other way hurt his Body; for there is in every man a certain high degree of feare through which he apprehends that
evill which is done to him to be the greatest, and therefore by naturall necessity he shuns it all he can, and 'tis
suppos'd he can doe no otherwise: When a man is arrived to this degree of fear, we cannot expect but he will
provide for himself either by flight, or fight. Since therefore no man is tyed to impossibilities, they who are
threatned either with deathe (which is the greatest evill to nature) or wounds, or some other bodily hurts, and are
not stout enough to bear them, are not obliged to endure them. Farthermore, he that is tyed by Contract is trusted,
(for Faith only is the Bond of Contracts) but they who are brought to punishment, either Capitall, or more gentle,
are fettered, or strongly guarded, which is a most certain signe that they seem'd not sufficiently bound from non
resistance by their Contracts. Its one thing if I promise thus: If I doe it not at the day appointed, kill me. Another
thing if thus: If I doe it not, though you should offer to kill me, I will not resist: All men, if need be, contract the
first way; but there is need sometimes. This second way, none, neither is it ever needfull; for in the meer state of
nature, if you have a mind to kill, that state it selfe affords you a Right; insomuch as you need not first trust him,
if for breach of trust you will afterward kill him. But in a Civill State, where the Right of life, and death, and of all
corporall punishment is with the Supreme; that same Right of killing cannot be granted to any private person.
Neither need the Supreme himselfe contract with any man patiently to yeeld to his punishment, but onely this, that
no man offer to defend others from him. If in the state of nature, as between two Cities, there should a Contract be
made, on condition of killing, if it were not perform'd, we must presuppose another Contract of not killing before
the appointed day. Wherefore on that day, if there be no performance, the right of Warre returnes; that is, an
hostile state, in which all things are lawfull, and therefore resistance also. Lastly, by the contract of not resisting,
we are oblig'd of two Evills to make choice of that which seemes the greater; for certaine Death is a greater evill
than Fighting; but of two Evills it is impossible not to chuse the least: By such a Compact therefore we should be
tyed to impossibilities, which is contrary to the very nature of compacts.

<section>XIX.</section> 
    Likewise no man is tyed by any Compacts whatsoever to accuse himself, or any other, by whose dammage
he is like to procure himselfe a bitter life; wherefore neither is a Father oblig'd to bear witnesse against his Sonne,
nor a Husband against his Wife, nor a Sonne against his Father; nor any man against any one, by whose meanes
he hath his subsistance; for in vain is that testimony which is presum'd to be corrupted from nature; but although
no man be tyed to accuse himself by any compact, yet in a publique tryall he may, by torture, be forc'd to make
answer; but such answers are no testimony of the fact, but helps for the searching out of truth; insomuch as
whether the party tortur'd his answer be true, or false, or whether he answer not at all, whatsoever he doth, he doth
it by Right.

<section>XX.</section> 
    Swearing is a speech joyned to a promise, whereby the promiser declares his renouncing of Gods mercy,
unlesse he perform his word; which definition is contained in the words themselves, which have in them the very
essence of an Oath, to wit, so God help me, or other equivalent, as with the Romans, Doe thou Jupiter so destroy
the deceiver, as I slay this same Beast: neither is this any let, but that an Oath may as well sometimes be
affirmatory, as promissory; for he that confirmes his affirmation with an Oath, promiseth that he speaks truth. But
though in some places it was the fashion for Subjects to Swear by their Kings; that custome took its Originall
hence, That those Kings took upon them Divine Honour; for Oathes were therefore introduc'd that by Religion,
and consideration of the Divine Power men might have a greater dread of breaking their Faiths, than that
wherewith they fear men, from whose eyes their actions may lie hid.

<section>XXI.</section> 
    Whence it followes, that an Oath must be conceived in that forme which he useth, who takes it; for in vain is
any man brought to Swear by a God whom he beleeves not, and therefore neither feares him. For though by the
light of nature it may be known that there is a God, yet no man thinks he is to Swear by him in any other fashion,
or by any other name than what is contain'd in the precepts of his own proper, that is, (as he who Swears
imagines) the true Religion.

<section>XXII.</section> 
    By the definition of an Oath we may understand, that a bare Contract obligeth no lesse, than that to which
we are Sworn; for it is the contract which binds us, the Oath relates to the Divine punishment, which it could not
provoke, if the breach of contract were not in its selfe unlawfull; but it could not be unlawfull if the Contract were
not obligatory. Furthermore, he that renounceth the mercy of God obligeth himselfe not to any punishment,
because it is ever lawfull to deprecate the punishment howsoever provok'd, and to enjoy Gods Pardon if it be
granted. The onely effect therefore of an Oath is this, To cause men who are naturally inclin'd to break all manner
of faith, through fear of punishment, to make the more Conscience of their words and actions.

<section>XXIII.</section> 
    To exact an Oath, where the breach of contract, if any be made, cannot but be known, and where the party
compacted, withall wants not power to punish, is to do somewhat more than is necessary unto self−defence, and
shewes a mind desirous not so much to benefit it selfe, as to prejudice another. For an Oath, out of the very form
of swearing, is taken in order to the provocation of Gods anger, that is to say, of him that is Omnipotent against
those who therefore violate their Faith, because they think that by their own strength they can escape the
punishment of men; and of him that is Omniscient against those, who therefore usually break their trust, because
they hope that no man shall see them.

<divider>____________</divider>
<footer>1. Right Reason.</footer> 
    By Right Reason in the naturall state of men, I understand not, as many doe, an infallible faculty, but the act 
    of reasoning, that is, the peculiar and true ratiocination of every man concerning those actions of his which may 
    either redound to the dammage, or benefit of his neighbours. I call it Peculiar, because although in a Civill 
    Government the reason of the Supreme (i.e. the Civill Law) is to be received by each single subject for the right; 
    yet being without this Civill Government, (in which state no man can know right reason from false, but by comparing 
    it with His owne) every mans owne reason is to be accounted not onely the rule of His owne actions which are done 
    at His owne perill, but also for the measure of another mans reason, in such things as doe concerne him. I call it 
    True; that is, concluding from true principles rightly fram'd, because that the whole breach of the Lawes of Nature 
    consists in the false reasoning, or rather folly of those men who see not those duties they are necessarily to performe 
    toward others in order to their owne conservation; but the Principles of Right reasoning about such like duties are 
    those which are explained in the 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, and 7. articles of the first Chapter.

<footer>2. Arise.</footer> 
    For, except there appear some new cause of fear, either from somewhat done, or some other token of the will not 
    to performe from the other part, it cannot be judg'd to be a just fear; for the cause which was not sufficient 
    to keep him from making Compact, must not suffice to authorize the breach of it, being made.

<chapter>Chapter III. Of the other Lawes of Nature.</chapter>

<section>I.</section> 
    Another of the Lawes of Nature is, to performe Contracts, or to keep trust; for it hath been shewed in the
foregoing Chapter that the Law of Nature commands every man, as a thing necessary, to obtain Peace; to
conveigh certain rights from each to other, and that this (as often as it shall happen to be done) is called a
Contract: But this is so farre forth onely conducible to peace, as we shall performe Our selves, what we contract
with others, shall be done, or omitted; and in vaine would Contracts be made, unlesse we stood to them. Because
therefore, to stand to our Covenants, Or to keep faith, is a thing necessary for the obtaining of peace, it will prove
by the second Article of the second Chapter to be a precept of the naturall Law.

<section>II.</section> 
    Neither is there in this matter, any exception of the persons, with whom we Contract, as if they keep no faith
with others; Or hold, that none ought to be kept, or are guilty of any other kind of vice: for he that Contracts, in
that he doth contract, denies that action to be in vaine, and it is against reason for a knowing man to doe a thing in
vain; and if he think himself not bound to keep it, in thinking so, he affirms the Contract to be made in vain: He
therefore, who Contracts with one with whom he thinks he is not bound to keep faith, he doth at once think a
Contract to be a thing done in vaine, and not in vaine, which is absurd. Either therefore we must hold trust with all
men, or else not bargain with them; that is, either there must be a declared Warre, Or a sure and faithfull Peace.

<section>III.</section> 
    The breaking of a Bargain, as also the taking back of a gift, (which ever consists in some action, Or omission)
is called an INJURY: But that action, or omission, is called unjust, insomuch as an injury, and an unjust action, or
omission, signifie the same thing, and both are the same with breach of Contract and trust: And it seemes the
word Injury came to be given to any action, or omission, because they were without Right. He that acted, or
omitted, having before conveyed his Right to some other. And there is some likenesse between that, which in the
common course of life we call Injury; and that, which in the Schools is usually called absurd. For even as he, who
by Arguments is driven to deny the Assertion which he first maintain'd, is said to be brought to an absurdity; in
like manner, he who through weaknesse of mind does, or omits that which before he had by Contract promis'd not
to doe, or omit, commits an Injury, and falls into no lesse contradiction, than he, who in the Schools is reduc'd to
an Absurdity. For by contracting for some future action, he wills it done; by not doing it, he wills it not done,
which is to will a thing done, and not done at the same time, which is a contradiction. An Injury therefore is a
kind of absurdity in conversation, as an absurdity is a kind of injury in disputation.

<section>IV.</section> 
    From these grounds it followes, that an injury can be done to no man [1] but him with whom we enter
Covenant, or to whom somewhat is made over by deed of gift, or to whom somwhat is promis'd by way of
bargain. And therefore damaging and injuring are often disjoyn'd: for if a Master command his Servant, who hath
promis'd to obey him, to pay a summe of money, or carry some present to a third man; the Servant, if he doe it
not, hath indeed damag'd this third party, but he injur'd his Master onely. So also in a civill government, if any
man offend another, with whom he hath made no Contract, he damages him to whom the evill is done, but he
injures none but him to whom the power of government belongs: for if he, who receives the hurt, should
expostulate the mischief; and he that did it, should answer thus, What art thou to me? Why should I rather doe
according to yours, than mine owne will, since I do not hinder, but you may do your own, and not my mind? In
which speech, where there hath no manner of pre−contract past, I see not, I confesse, what is reprehensible.

<section>V.</section> 
    These words just, and unjust, as also justice, and injustice, are equivocall; for they signifie one thing when they
are attributed to Persons, another when to actions: When they are attributed to Actions, Just signifies as much as
what's done with Right, and unjust, as what's done with injury: he who hath done some just thing is not therefore
said to be a just Person, but guiltlesse, and he that hath done some unjust thing, we doe not therefore say he is an
unjust, but guilty man. But when the words are applyed to Persons; to be just, signifies as much as to be delighted
in just dealing, to study how to doe righteousnesse, or to indeavour in all things to doe that which is just; and to be
unjust, is to neglect righteous dealing, or to think it is to be measured not according to my contract, but some
present benefit; so as the justice or injustice of the mind, the intention, or the man, is one thing; that of an action,
or omission, another; and innumerable actions of a just man may be unjust, and of an unjust man, just: But that
man is to be accounted just, who doth just things because the Law commands it, unjust things only by reason of
his infirmity; and he is properly said to be unjust who doth righteousness for fear of the punishment annext unto
the Law, and unrighteousnesse by reason of the iniquity of his mind.

<section>VI.</section> 
    The justice of actions is commonly distinguisht into two kinds; Commutative, and Distributive, the former
whereof they say consists in Arithmeticall, the latter in Geometricall proportion: and that is conversant in
exchanging, in buying, selling, borrowing, lending, location, and conduction, and other acts whatsoever belonging
to Contracters, where, if there be an equall return made, hence they say springs a commutative justice: But this is
busied about the dignity, and merits of men; so as if there be rendred to every man kata pen axian more to him
who is more worthy, and lesse to him that deserves lesse, and that proportionably, hence they say ariseth
distributive justice: I acknowledge here some certaine distinction of equality; to wit, that one is an equality simply
so called, as when two things of equall value are compar'd together, as a pound of silver with twelve ounces of the
same silver; the other is an equality, secundum quod; as when a 1000 pound is to be divided to an hundred men,
600 pounds are given to 60 men, and 400 to 40 where there is no equality between 600 and 400. But when it
happens, that there is the same inequality in the number of them to whom it is distributed, every one of them shall
take an equall part, whence it is called an equall distribution: But such like equality is the same thing with
Geometricall proportion. But what is all this to Justice? for neither, if I sell my goods for as much as I can get for
them, doe I injure the buyer, who sought, and desir'd them of me? neither if I divide more of what is mine to him
who deserves lesse, so long as I give the other what I have agreed for, do I wrong to either? which truth our
Saviour himself, being God, testifies in the Gospell. This therefore is no distinction of Justice, but of equality; yet
perhaps it cannot be deny'd, but that Justice is a certain equality, as consisting in this onely; that since we are all
equall by nature, one should not arrogate more Right to himselfe, than he grants to another, unlesse he have fairly
gotten it by Compact. And let this suffice to be spoken against this distinction of Justice, although now almost
generally receiv'd by all, lest any man should conceive an injury to be somewhat else, than the breach of Faith, or
Contract, as hath been defin'd above.

<section>VII.</section> 
    It is an old saying, Volenti non fit iniuria (the willing man receives no injury) yet the truth of it may be
deriv'd from our Principles. For grant, that a man be willing that that should be done, which he conceives to be an
injury. to him; why then that is done by his will, which by Contract was not lawfull to be done; but he being
willing that should be done, which was not lawfull by Contract, the Contract it self (by the 15. Article of the
foregoing Chapter) becomes void: The Right therefore of doing it returnes, therefore it is done by Right;
wherefore it is no injury.

<section>VIII.</section> 
    The third precept of the Naturall Law, is, That you suffer not him to be the worse for you, who out of the
confidence he had in you, first did you a good turn; or that you accept not a gift, but with a mind to endeavour,
that the giver shall have no just occasion to repent him of his gift. For without this he should act without reason
that would conferre a benefit where he sees it would be lost; and by this meanes all beneficence, and trust,
together with all kind of benevolence would be taken from among men, neither would there be ought of mutuall
assistance among them, nor any commencement of gaining grace and favour; by reason whereof the state of
Warre would necessarily remain, contrary to the fundamentall Law of Nature: But because the breach of this Law
is not a breach of trust, or contract, (for we suppose no Contracts to have pass'd among them) therefore is it not
usually termed an injury, but because good turns and thankes have a mutuall eye to each other, it is called
INGRATITUDE.

<section>IX.</section> 
    The fourth precept of Nature, is, That every man render himself usefull unto others: which, that we may
rightly understand, we must remember that there is in men, a diversity of dispositions to enter into society, arising
from the diversity of their affections, not unlike that which is found in stones, brought together in the Building, by
reason of the diversity of their matter, and figure. For as a stone, which in regard of its sharp and angular form
takes up more room from other stones than it fils up it selfe, neither because of the hardnesse of its matter cannot
well be prest together, or easily cut, and would hinder the building from being fitly compacted, is cast away, as
not fit for use: so a man, who for the harshness of his disposition in retaining superfluities for himself, and
detaining of necessaries from others, and being incorrigible, by reason of the stubbornnesse of his affections, is
commonly said to be uselesse, and troublesome unto others. Now, because each one not by Right onely, but even
by naturall necessity is suppos'd, with all his main might, to intend the procurement of those things which are
necessary to his own preservation; if any man will contend on the other side for superfluities, by his default there
will arise a Warre, because that on him alone there lay no necessity of contending, he therefore acts against the
fundamentall Law of Nature: Whence it followes (which wee were to shew) that it is a precept of nature; That
every man accommodate himselfe to others. But he who breaks this Law may be called uselesse, and
troublesome. Yet Cicero opposeth inhumanity to this usefulnesse, as having regard to this very Law.

<section>X.</section> 
    The fifth precept of the Law of nature is: That we must forgive him who repents, and asketh pardon for what is
past; having first taken caution for the time to come. The pardon of what is past, or the remission of an offence, is
nothing else but the granting of Peace to him that asketh it, after he hath warr'd against us, and now is become
penitent. But Peace granted to him that repents not, that is, to him that retains an hostile mind, or that gives not
caution for the future; that is, seeks not Peace, but oportunity, is not properly Peace but feare, and therefore is not
commanded by nature. Now to him that will not pardon the penitent, and that gives future caution, peace it selfe it
seems is not pleasing; which is contrary to the naturall Law.

<section>XI.</section> 
    The sixth precept of the naturall Law is, That in revenge and punishments we must have our eye not at the
evill past, but the future good. That is: It is not lawfull to inflict punishment for any other end, but that the
offender may be corrected, or that others warned by his punishment may become better. But this is confirmed
chiefly from hence, that each man is bound by the law of nature to forgive one another, provided he give caution
for the future, as hath been shewed in the foregoing Article. Furthermore, because revenge, if the time past be
onely considered, is nothing else but a certain triumph, and glory of minde, which points at no end, (for it
contemplates onely what is past; but the end is a thing to come) but that which is directed to no end is vain; That
revenge therefore which regards not the future, proceeds from vaine glory, and therefore without reason. But to
hurt another without reason introduces a warre, and is contrary to the fundamentall Law of Nature; It is therefore
a precept of the Law of nature, that in revenge wee look not backwards but forward. Now the breach of this Law,
is commonly called CRUELTY.

<section>XII.</section> 
    But because all signes of hatred, and contempt provoke most of all to brawling and fighting, insomuch as
most men would rather lose their lives, (that I say not their Peace) than suffer reproach; it followes in the seventh
place, That it is prescribed by the Law of nature, that no man either by deeds, or words, countenance, or laughter,
doe declare himselfe to hate, or scorne another. The breach of which Law is called Reproach. But although
nothing be more frequent than the scoffes and jeers of the powerfull against the weak, and namely of Judges
against guilty persons, which neither relate to the offence of the guilty, nor the duty of the Judges, yet these kind
of men do act against the Law of nature, and are to be esteemed for contumelious.

<section>XIII.</section> 
    The question whether of two men be the more worthy, belongs not to the naturall, but civill state; for it hath
been shewed before, Chap. I. Art. 3. that all men by nature are equall, and therefore the inequality which now is,
suppose from riches, power, nobility of kindred, is come from the civill Law. I know that Aristotle in his first
book of Politiques affirmes as a foundation of the whole politicall science, that some men by nature are made
worthy to command, others onely to serve; as if Lord and Master were distinguished not by consent of men, but
by an aptnesse, that is, a certain kind of naturall knowledge, or ignorance; which foundation is not onely against
reason (as but now hath been shewed) but also against experience: for neither almost is any man so dull of
understanding as not to judge it better to be ruled by himselfe, than to yeeld himselfe to the government of
another; neither if the wiser and stronger doe contest, have these ever, or often the upper hand of those. Whether
therefore men be equall by nature, the equality is to be acknowledged, or whether unequall, because they are like
to contest for dominion, its necessary for the obtaining of Peace, that they be esteemed as equall; and therefore it
is in the eight place a precept of the Law of nature, That every man be accounted by nature equall to another, the
contrary to which Law is PRIDE.

<section>XIV.</section> 
    As it was necessary to the conservation of each man, that he should part with some of his Rights, so it is no
lesse necessary to the same conservation, that he retain some others, to wit the Right of bodily protection, of free
enjoyment of ayre, water, and all necessaries for life. Since therefore many common Rights are retained by those
who enter into a peaceable state, and that many peculiar ones are also acquired, hence ariseth this ninth dictate of
the naturall Law, to wit, That what Rights soever any man challenges to himselfe, he also grant the same as due to
all the rest: otherwise he frustrates the equality acknowledged in the former Article. For what is it else to
acknowledge an equality of persons in the making up of society, but to attribute equall Right and Power to those
whom no reason would else engage to enter into society? But to ascribe equall things to equalls, is the same with
giving things proportionall to proportionals. The observation of this Law is called MEEKNES, the violation
pleonexia, the breakers by the Latines are styled Immodici et immodesti.

<section>XV.</section> 
    In the tenth place it is commanded by the Law of nature, That every man in dividing Right to others, shew
himselfe equall to either party. By the foregoing Law we are forbidden to assume more Right by nature to our
selves, than we grant to others. We may take lesse if we will, for that sometimes is an argument of modesty. But if
at any time matter of Right be to be divided by us unto others, we are forbidden by this Law to favour one more or
lesse than another. For he that by favouring one before another, observes not this naturall equality, reproaches him
whom he thus undervalues: but it is declared above, that a reproach is against the Lawes of Nature. The
observance of this Precept is called EQUITY; the breach, Respect of Persons. The Greeks in one word term it
prosopolepsia.

<section>XVI.</section> 
    From the foregoing Law is collected this eleventh, Those things which cannot be divided, must be used in
common, (if they can) and (that the quantity of the matter permit) every man as much as he lists, but if the
quantity permit not, then with limitation, and proportionally to the number of the users: for otherwise that equality
can by no means be observed, which we have shewed in the forgoing Article to be commanded by the Law of
Nature.

<section>XVII.</section> 
    Also what cannot be divided, nor had in common, it is provided by the Law of nature (which may be the
twelfth Precept) that the use of that thing be either by turns, or adjudged to one onely by lot, and that in the using
it by turns, it be also decided by lot who shall have the first use of it; For here also regard is to be had unto
equality: but no other can be found, but that of lot.

<section>XVIII.</section> 
    But all lot is twofold; arbitrary, or naturall; Arbitrary is that which is cast by the consent of the Contenders,
and it consists in meer chance (as they say) or fortune. Naturall is primogeniture (in Greek klironomia, as it were
given by lot) or first possession. Therefore the things which can neither be divided, nor had in common, must be
granted to the first possessour, as also those things which belonged to the Father are due to the Sonne, unlesse the
Father himselfe have formerly conveighed away that Right to some other. Let this therefore stand for the
thirteenth Law of Nature.

<section>XIX.</section> 
    The 14. Precept of the Law of nature is; That safety must be assured to the mediators for Peace. For the
reason which commands the end, commands also the means necessary to the end. But the first dictate of Reason is
Peace. All the rest are means to obtain it, and without which Peace cannot be had. But neither can Peace be had
without mediation, nor mediation without safety; it is therefore a dictate of Reason, that is, a Law of nature, That
we must give all security to the Mediators for Peace.

<section>XX.</section> 
    Furthermore, because, although men should agree to make all these, and whatsoever other Lawes of Nature,
and should endeavour to keep them, yet doubts, and controversies would daily arise concerning the application of
them unto their actions, to wit, whether what was done, were against the Law, or not, (which we call, the question
of Right) whence will follow a fight between Parties, either sides supposing themselves wronged; it is therefore
necessary to the preservation of Peace (because in this case no other fit remedy can possibly be thought on) that
both the disagreeing Parties refer the matter unto some third, and oblige themselves by mutuall compacts to stand
to his judgement in deciding the controversie. And he to whom they thus refer themselves is called an Arbiter. It
is therefore the 15. Precept of the naturall Law, That both parties disputing concerning the matter of right submit
themselves unto the opinion and judgement of some third.

<section>XXI.</section> 
    But from this ground, that an Arbiter or Judge is chosen by the differing Parties to determine the
controversie, we gather, that the Arbiter must not be one of the Parties: for every man is presumed to seek what is
good for himselfe naturally, and what is just, onely for Peaces sake, and accidentally; and therefore cannot
observe that same equality commanded by the Law of nature so exactly as a third man would do: It is therefore in
the sixteenth place contained in the Law of nature, That no man must be Judge or Arbiter in his own cause.

<section>XXII.</section> 
    From the same ground followes in the seventeenth place, That no man must be Judge who propounds unto
himself any hope of profit, or glory, from the victory of either part: for the like reason swayes here, as in the
foregoing Law.

<section>XXIII.</section> 
    But when there is some controversie of the fact it selfe, to wit, whether that bee done or not, which is said
to bee done, the naturall Law wills, that the Arbiter trust both Parties alike, that is, (because they affirm
contradictories) that hee believe neither: He must therefore give credit to a third, or a third and fourth, or more,
that he may be able to give judgement of the fact, as often as by other signes he cannot come to the knowledge of
it. The 18. Law of nature therefore injoynes Arbiters, and Judges of fact, That where firm and certain signes of the
fact appear not, there they rule their sentence by such witnesses, as seem to be indifferent to both Parts.

<section>XXIV.</section> 
    From the above declared definition of an Arbiter may be furthermore understood, That no contract or
promise must Passe between him and the parties whose Judge he is appointed, by vertue whereof he may be
engaged to speak in favour of either part, nay, or be oblig'd to judge according to equity, or to pronounce such
sentence as he shall truly judge to be equall. The Judge is indeed bound to give such sentence as he shall judge to
be equall by the Law of Nature recounted in the 15. Article. To the obligation of which Law nothing can be added
by way of Compact. Such compact therefore would be in vain. Besides, if giving wrong judgement, he should
contend for the equity of it, except such Compact be of no force, the Controversie would remain after Judgement
given, which is contrary to the constitution of an Arbiter, who is so chosen, as both parties have oblig'd
themselves to stand to the judgement which he should pronounce. The Law of Nature therefore commands the
Judge to be disengaged, which is its 19. precept.

<section>XXV.</section> 
    Farthermore, forasmuch as the Lawes of Nature are nought else but the dictates of Reason, so as, unlesse a
man endeavour to preserve the faculty of right reasoning, he cannot observe the Lawes of Nature, it is manifest,
that he, who knowingly, or willingly, doth ought, whereby the rationall faculty may be destroyed, or weakned, he
knowingly, and willingly, breaks the Law of nature: For there is no difference between a man who performes not
his Duty, and him who does such things willingly, as make it impossible for him to doe it. But they destroy and
weaken the reasoning faculty, who doe that which disturbs the mind from its naturall state; that which most
manifestly happens to Drunkards and Gluttons; we therefore sin in the 20. place against the Law of Nature by
Drunkennesse.

<section>XXVI.</section> 
    Perhaps some man, who sees all these precepts of Nature deriv'd by a certain artifice from the single
dictate of Reason advising us to look to the preservation, and safegard of our selves, will say, That the deduction
of these Lawes is so hard, that it is not to be expected they will be vulgarly known, and therefore neither will they
prove obliging: for Lawes, if they be not known, oblige not, nay, indeed are not Lawes. To this I answer, it's true,
That hope, fear, anger, ambition, covetousnesse, vain glory, and other perturbations of mind, doe hinder a man so,
as he cannot attaine to the knowledge of these Lawes, whilst those passions prevail in him: But there is no man
who is not sometimes in a quiet mind; At that time therefore there is nothing easier for him to know, though he be
never so rude and unlearn'd, than this only Rule, That when he doubts, whether what he is now doing to another,
may be done by the Law of Nature, or not, he conceive himselfe to be in that others stead. Here instantly those
perturbations which perswaded him to the fact, being now cast into the other scale, disswade him as much: And
this Rule is not onely easie, but is Anciently celebrated in these words, Quod tibi fieri non vis, alteri ne feceris:
Do not that to others, you would not have done to your self.

<section>XXVII.</section> 
    But because most men, by reason of their perverse desire of present profit, are very unapt to observe these
Lawes, although acknowledg'd by them, if perhaps some others more humble than the rest should exercise that
equity and usefulnesse which Reason dictates, those not practising the same, surely they would not follow Reason
in so doing; nor would they hereby procure themselves peace, but a more certain quick destruction, and the
keepers of the Law become a meer prey to the breakers of it. It is not therefore to be imagin'd, that by Nature,
(that is, by Reason) men are oblig'd to the exercise of all these Lawes [2] in that state of men wherein they are not
practis'd by others. We are oblig'd yet in the interim to a readinesse of mind to observe them whensoever their
observation shall seeme to conduce to the end for which they were ordain'd. We must therefore conclude, that the
Law of Nature doth alwayes, and every where oblige in the internall Court, or that of Conscience, but not alwayes
in the externall Court, but then onely when it may be done with safety.

<section>XXVIII.</section> 
    But the Lawes which oblige Conscience, may be broken by an act, not onely contrary to them, but also
agreeable with them, if so be that he who does it be of another opinion: for though the act it self be answerable to
the Lawes, yet his Conscience is against them.

<section>XXIX.</section> 
    The Lawes of Nature are immutable, and eternall; What they forbid, can never be lawfull; what they
command, can never be unlawfull: For pride, ingratitude, breach of Contracts (or injury), inhumanity, contumely,
will never be lawfull; nor the contrary vertues to these ever unlawfull, as we take them for dispositions of the
mind, that is, as they are considered in the Court of Conscience, where onely they oblige, and are Lawes. Yet
actions may be so diversified by circumstances, and the Civill Law, that what's done with equity at one time, is
guilty of iniquity at another; and what suits with reason at one time, is contrary to it another. Yet Reason is still
the same, and changeth not her end, which is Peace, and Defence; nor of the minde which the meanes to attaine
them, to wit, those vertues we have declar'd above, and which cannot be abrogated by any Custome, or Law
whatsoever.

<section>XXX.</section> 
    It's evident by what hath hitherto been said, how easily the Lawes of Nature are to be observ'd, because
they require the endeavour onely, (but that must be true and constant) which who so shall performe, we may
rightly call him JUST. For he who tends to this with his whole might, namely, that his actions be squar'd
according to the precepts of Nature, he shewes clearly that he hath a minde to fulfill all those Lawes, which is all
we are oblig'd to by rationall nature. Now he that hath done all he is oblig'd to, is a Just Man.

<section>XXXI.</section> 
    All Writers doe agree that the Naturall Law is the same with the Morall. Let us see wherefore this is true.
We must know therefore, that Good and Evill are names given to things to signifie the inclination, or aversion of
them by whom they were given. But the inclinations of men are diverse, according to their diverse Constitutions,
Customes, Opinions; as we may see in those things we apprehend by sense, as by tasting, touching, smelling; but
much more in those which pertain to the common actions of life, where what this man commends, (that is to say,
calls Good) the other undervalues, as being Evil; Nay, very often the same man at diverse times, praises, and
dispraises the same thing. Whilst thus they doe, necessary it is there should be discord, and strife: They are
therefore so long in the state of War, as by reason of the diversity of the present appetites, they mete Good and
Evill by diverse measures. All men easily acknowledge this state, as long as they are in it, to be evill, and by
consequence that Peace is good. They therefore who could not agree concerning a present, doe agree concerning a
future Good, which indeed is a work of Reason; for things present are obvious to the sense, things to come to our
Reason only. Reason declaring Peace to be good, it followes by the same reason, that all the necessary means to
Peace be good also, and therefore, that Modesty, Equity, Trust, Humanity, Mercy (which we have demonstrated
to be necessary to Peace) are good Manners, or habits, (that is) Vertues. The Law therefore, in the means to Peace,
commands also Good Manners, or the practise of Vertue: And therefore it is call'd Morall.

<section>XXXII.</section> 
    But because men cannot put off this same irrationall appetite, whereby they greedily prefer the present
good (to which, by strict consequence, many unforeseen evills doe adhere) before the future, it happens, that
though all men doe agree in the commendation of the foresaid vertues, yet they disagree still concerning their
Nature, to wit, in what each of them doth consist; for as oft as anothers good action displeaseth any man, that
action hath the name given of some neighbouring vice; likewise the bad actions, which please them, are ever
entituled to some Vertue; whence it comes to passe that the same Action is prais'd by these, and call'd Vertue, and
dispraised by those, and termed vice. Neither is there as yet any remedy found by Philosophers for this matter; for
since they could not observe the goodnesse of actions to consist in this, that it was in order to Peace, and the evill
in this, that it related to discord, they built a morall Philosophy wholly estranged from the morall Law, and
unconstant to it self; for they would have the nature of vertues seated in a certain kind of mediocrity betweene two
extremes, and the vices in the extremes themselves; which is apparently false: For to dare is commended, and
under the name of fortitude is taken for a vertue, although it be an extreme, if the cause be approved. Also the
quantity of a thing given, whether it be great, or little, or between both, makes not liberality, but the cause of
giving it. Neither is it injustice, if I give any man more, of what is mine own, than I owe him. The Lawes of
Nature therefore are the summe of Morall Philosophy, whereof I have onely delivered such precepts in this place,
as appertain to the preservation of our selves against those dangers which arise from discord. But there are other
precepts of rationall nature, from whence spring other vertues: for temperance also is a precept of Reason,
because intemperance tends to sicknesse, and death. And so fortitude too, (that is) that same faculty of resisting
stoutly in present dangers, (and which are more hardly declined than overcome) because it is a means tending to
the preservation of him that resists.

<section>XXXIII.</section> 
    But those which we call the Lawes of nature (since they are nothing else but certain conclusions
understood by Reason, of things to be done, and omitted; but a Law to speak properly and accurately, is the
speech of him who by Right commands somewhat to others to be done, or omitted) are not (in propriety of
speech) Lawes, as they proceed from nature; yet as they are delivered by God in holy Scriptures, (as we shall see
in the Chapter following) they are most properly called by the name of Lawes: for the sacred Scripture is the
speech of God commanding over all things by greatest Right.

<divider>____________</divider>
<footer>1. Injury can be done to no man.</footer> 
    The word injustice relates to some Law: Injury to some Person, as well as some Law. For what's unjust, is unjust 
    to all; but there may an injury be done, and yet not against me, nor thee, but some other; and sometimes against 
    no private Person, but the Magistrate only; sometimes also neither against the Magistrate, nor any private man, but 
    onely against God; for through Contract, and conveighance of Right, we say, that an injury is done against this, or 
    that man. Hence it is (which we see in all kind of Government) that what private men contract between themselves by 
    word, or writing, is releast againe at the will of the Obliger. But those mischiefes which are done against the Lawes 
    of the Land, as theft, homicide, and the like, are punisht not as he wills, to whom the hurt is done, but according to 
    the will of the Magistrate; that is, the constituted Lawes.

<footer>2. The exercise of all these Lawes.</footer> 
    Nay among these Lawes some things there are, the omission whereof (provided it be done for Peace, or Self−preservation) 
    seemes rather to be the fulfilling, than breach of the Naturall Law; for he that doth all things against those that doe 
    all things, and plunders plunderers, doth equity; but on the other side, to doe that which in Peace is an handsome action, 
    and becomming an honest man, is dejectednesse, and Poornesse of spirit, and a betraying of ones self in the time of War, 
    But there are certain naturall Lawes, whose exercise ceaseth not even in the time of War it self; for I cannot understand 
    what drunkennesse, or cruelty (that is, Revenge which respects not the future good) can advance toward Peace, or the 
    preservation of any man. Briefly, in the state of nature, what's just, and unjust, is not to be esteem'd by the Actions, 
    but by the Counsell, and Conscience of the Actor. That which is done out of necessity, out of endeavour for Peace, for the 
    preservation of our selves, is done with Right; otherwise every damage done to a man would be a breach of the naturall Law, 
    and an injury against God.
</excerpt>